SAAD AHMED

Curriculum Vitae

Technology Square Research Building School of Interactive Computing, Atlanta, GA ⑤ (+1) 7738238029 ☐ sahmed@gatech.edu ☐ https://www.saadahmedch.com in Linkedin

Research Interests

I build a **sustainable** future for computing by enabling the **Internet of Batteryless Things**; a vision that liberates Internet of Things (IoT) devices from batteries thus allowing maintenance-free operation. I develop **system support** that cuts across the system stack to ensure **energy-efficient**, **reliable**, **and adaptive** program execution while making computational progress under frequent power failures. I actively look to apply my work in mobile health, education, smart cities, and environmental monitoring to unlock new **applications**.

My work has appeared in the top computing journals and conferences such as **IMWUT**, **SenSys**, **IPSN**, **EuroSys**, **ACM TECS**, and **ACM TCPS**. It has been nominated for the **best paper award (EWSN)**, invited to the GetMobile magazine for the SIGMOBILE research highlight, and named a finalist for **Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award**. My work has been covered by top media outlets such ACM Tech News, Forbes, Tech Crunch, Gizmodo, and many more. As recognition of my work, I was selected for the prestigious **Alexandar Von Humboldt Postdoctoral Fellowship** and nominated for the College of Computing **Outstanding Postdoctoral Researcher Award** at the Georgia Institute of Technology.

Education

2016–2020 **PhD, Computer Science**, LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan.

Dissertation: Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing

Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai

2014–2016 MS, Computer Science, LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan.

Advisor: Dr. Asim Karim

2009–2013 **BS, Computer Science**, National University of Computer and Emerging Sciences, Pakistan.

Project: *PL/SQL to MySQL Conversion* Advisor: Dr. Fakhar-ul-Islam Lodhi

Bronze Medal: Among top 2% in a batch of 200 students

Selected Publications

EuroSys'23 Efficient and Safe I/O Operations for Intermittent Systems.

Eren Yildiz, <u>Saad Ahmed*</u>, Bashima Islam, Josiah Hester, Kasim Sinan Yildirim To appear in European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys'23)

Acceptance rate = 14%

* Lead advisor for the student

SenSys'22 **Protean: Adaptive Battery-free Computing Platform**.

Abu Bakar, Rishabh Goel, Jasper de Winkel, Jason Huang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Przemysław Pawełczak, Kasım Sinan Yıldırım, Josiah Hester

InACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys'22)

ACM SIGMOBILE Research highlight

UbiComp'22 Battery-free MakeCode: Accessible Programming for Intermittent Computing.

Chris Kraemer, Amy Guo, Saad Ahmed, Josiah Hester

ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

Covered by Microsoft Research, ACM Tech News, and Hackster.io and many more

UbiComp'22 FaceBit: Smart Facemask Platform.

Alexander Curtiss, Blaine Rothrock, Abu Bakar, Nivedita Arora, Jason Huang, Zachary Englehardt, Aaron-Patrick Empedrado, Chixiang Wang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Yang Zhang, Nabil Alshurafa, Josiah Hester ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist

Covered by Top media outlets including Scientific American, TechCrunch, Forbes, Gizmodo and many more.

EWSN'20 Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Qurat-ul-Ain, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola, Muhammad Hamad Alizai International Conference on Embedded Wireless Systems and Networks (EWSN'20)

TBest Paper Nominee

Academic Achievements & Recognitions

- 2023 Nomination for the College of Computing Postdoctoral Researcher Award
- 2023 Protean selected for the ACM SIGMOBILE Research Highlight
- 2022 FaceBit was the Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist
- 2021 Selection for the prestigious **Alexander Von Humboldt** postdoctoral fellowship, Germany.
- 2020 D²VFS nominated for **Best Paper Award** at EWSN
- 2017 First position in Intermittent Computing Hackathon at IDEA League Doctoral School
- 2013 **Bronze Medal**, Faculty of Computing, NUCES, Pakistan
- 2010-12 **Dean's Honor List**, Faculty of Computing, NUCES, Pakistan
 - 2013 Final Year Project among **top 10%**, Faculty of Computing, NUCES
 - 2010 Merit Based Selection for visiting UK's & EU's Top Universities, Govt. of Punjab, Pakistan
- 2009-13 National Talent Scholarship, Govt. of Punjab, Pakistan
 - 2009 Academic Roll of Honour, Govt. College University Lahore, Pakistan
 - 2009 **Gold Medal**, Higher Secondary School Exam, Pakistan

Research Impact

8 peer-reviewed conference papers (all are A or A* conferences as per CORE 2018)

3 peer-reviewed papers in ACM Transactions journals **3** refereed poster abstracts

Professional Experience

Georgia Institute of Technology, USA

Oct 2022 – **Postdoctoral Researcher**Present **Mentor: Dr. Josiah Hester**.

Northwestern University, USA

Dec 2020 – **Postdoctoral Researcher** Sep 2022 **Mentor: Dr. Josiah Hester**.

Techlogix Inc., Pakistan

May 2013 – **Software Engineer**. Nov 2014

Research Experience

LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan

May 2020 - Research Associate

Nov 2020 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

May 2016 - Graduate Research Assistant

Nov 2020 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

RWTH Aachen, Germany

July 2016, Visiting Researcher
Aug 2017 Host: Dr. Klause Wehrle.

LUMS School of Science and Engineering, Pakistan

Jan 2016 - Research Assistant

Aug 2016 Advisor: Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai.

Community Service

Peer Review

Feb. 2023 IMWUT

Feb. 2023 Ad Hoc Networks

Oct. 2022 Journal of Systems Architecture

March. 2021 Ad Hoc Networks

July 2020 Oct. 2019	IEEE Transactions on Mobile Computing ACM Transactions on Sensor Networks International Journal of Computer and Telecommunications Networking IEEE International Conference on Parallel and Distributed Systems (ICPADS)
July 2022	Undergraduate Research Judge for the undergraduate research expo, Northwestern University
	Talks
Nov-2020	Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing, University of Southampton, UK
Nov-2020	Fast and Energy-efficient Intermittent Computing, KTH Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm, Sweden
Feb-2020	Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling, EWSN, Lyon, France
June-2019	Differential Checkpointing for Intermittent Programs, LCTES, Phoenix AZ, USA
June-2019	Finding the Missing Joules of Transiently-powered Computers, LCTES, Phoenix AZ, USA
Aug-2016	Incremental Checkpoints for Interruptible Computations, RWTH Aachen, Aachen, Germany
	Fellowships & Grants
2021	Alexander Von Humboldt Research Fellowship (Selection), Germany
2020	National Data Center Travel Grant to attend EWSN, LUMS
2019	Student Travel Grant worth to attend LCTES, LUMS
2018	CPS Week Travel Grant to attend IPSN, CPS Week
2017	Travel Grant to attend Doctoral Colloquium at RWTH Aachen, DAAD
2016	Travel Grant to attend Doctoral Colloquium at RWTH Aachen, DAAD

Publications

In Conference Proceedings

C8 Efficient and Safe I/O Operations for Intermittent Systems.

Eren Yildiz, <u>Saad Ahmed*</u>, Bashima Islam, Josiah Hester, Kasim Sinan Yildirim To appear in European Conference on Computer Systems (EuroSys'23)

Acceptance rate = 14%

^{*} Lead advisor for the student

C7 Protean: Adaptive Battery-free Computing Platform.

Abu Bakar, Rishabh Goel, Jasper de Winkel, Jason Huang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Bashima Islam, Przemysław Pawełczak, Kasım Sinan Yıldırım, Josiah Hester

In ACM Conference on Embedded Networked Sensor Systems (SenSys'22)

ACM SIGMOBILE Research highlight

C6 Battery-free MakeCode: Accessible Programming for Intermittent Computing.

Chris Kraemer, Amy Guo, Saad Ahmed, Josiah Hester

ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

Covered by Microsoft Research, ACM Tech News, and Hackster.io and many more

C5 FaceBit: Smart Facemask Platform.

Alexander Curtiss, Blaine Rothrock, Abu Bakar, Nivedita Arora, Jason Huang, Zachary Englehardt, Aaron-Patrick Empedrado, Chixiang Wang, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Yang Zhang, Nabil Alshurafa, Josiah Hester ACM Conference on Pervasive and Ubiquitous Computing (UbiComp'22)

Published in PACM IMWUT, Volume 5, Issue 4

Fast Company's Innovation by Design Award Finalist

Covered by Top media outlets including Scientific American, Forbes, TechCrunch, Gizmodo and many more.

C4 No-frills Water Comfort for Developing Regions.

Samar Abbas, Ahmed Ehsan, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Sheraz Ali Khan, Tariq Muhammad Jadoon, Muhammad Hamad Alizai

International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN'20)

C3 Intermittent Computing with Dynamic Voltage and Frequency Scaling.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Qurat-u-Ain, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola, Muhammad Hamad Alizai International Conference on Embedded Wireless Systems and Networks (EWSN'20)

P Best Paper Nominee

C2 The betrayal of constant power× time: Finding the missing joules of transiently-powered computers.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Abu Bakar, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola

Proceedings of the 20th ACM SIGPLAN/SIGBED International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded Systems (LCTES'19)

C1 Efficient intermittent computing with differential checkpointing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola Proceedings of the 20th ACM SIGPLAN/SIGBED International Conference on Languages, Compilers, and Tools for Embedded Systems (LCTES'19)

Journal Articles

J3 ASHRAY: Enhancing Water-usage Comfort in Developing Regions using Data-driven IoT Retrofits.

Samar Abbas, Ahmed Ehsan, <u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Sheraz Ali Khan, Tariq Muhammad Jadoon, Muhammad Hamad Alizai

ACM Transactions on Cyber-Physical Systems (TCPS)

J2 Fast and Energy-efficient State Checkpointing for Intermittent Computing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola ACM Transactions on Embedded Computing Systems (TECS)

J1 Demystifying Energy Consumption Dynamics in Transiently-powered Computers.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Nawaz, Abu Bakar, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Luca Mottola

ACM Transactions on Embedded Computing Systems (TECS)

Workshops & Posters

W3 Towards smaller checkpoints for better intermittent computing.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Luca Mottola 17th ACM/IEEE International Conference on Information Processing in Sensor Networks (IPSN'18)

W2 Incremental Checkpointing Techniques for Transiently Powered Computers.

Saad Ahmed

Doctoral School on Transiently Powered Computing-Collocated with SenSys'17

W1 Incremental checkpointing for interruptible computations.

<u>Saad Ahmed</u>, Muhammad Hamad Alizai, Junaid Haroon Siddiqui, Naveed Anwar Bhatti, Luca Mottola Proceedings of the 14th ACM Conference on Embedded Network Sensor Systems (SenSys'16)

In Preparation

P2 Battery-less Health Sensing powered by Intra-body Power Transfer.

Saad Ahmed, Eren Yildiz, Bashima Islam, Kasim Sinan Yildirim, Josiah Hester

P1 Data Cache for Intermittent Computing Systems with Non-Volatile Main Memory.

Vito Kortbeek, Sourav Mohapatra, Saad Ahmed, Przemysław Pawełczak

Teaching Experience

Spring, 2022: **Internet of Things**, Co-Instructor, Northwestern University.

Fall, 2020: Introduction to Internet of Things, Co-Instructor, LUMS.

Fall, 2018: Internet of Things, Teaching Assistant, LUMS.

Fall, 2014: **Operating Systems**, Teaching Assistant, NUCES.

Spring, 2014: **Operating Systems**, Lab Instructor, NUCES.

Operating Systems, Teaching Assistant, NUCES.

Fall, 2013: Operating Systems, Teaching Assistant, NUCES.

Fall, 2013: **Operating Systems**, Teaching Assistant, NUCES.

Operating Systems, Lab Instructor, NUCES.

Student Mentorship

2023	Shashank Holla , Research Assistant, Georgia Institute of Technology (now at NVIDIA).
2022-2023	Eren Yildiz , Visiting Student, Northwestern University (now at Ege University, Turkey).
2019-2020	Qurat-ul-Ain, MS-Thesis, LUMS.
2018-2019	Muhamamd Nawaz, Research Assistant, LUMS (now at SIEMENS).
2017-2018	Abu Bakar, Research Assistant, LUMS (now at Georgia Institute of Technology).
2016-2017	Hassan Ali Khan, MS-Thesis, LUMS (now at NC State University).
2016-2017	Ans Fida, Undergraduate Research Assistant, LUMS (now at SalesForce).
2016-2017	Kamran Khalil, Undergraduate Research Assistant, LUMS (now at Purdue University).
2016-2017	Natasha Khan, MS-Thesis, LUMS (now at CERN).

References

Dr. Muhammad Hamad Alizai

Associate Professor,

Department of Computer Science

LUMS, Pakistan

⊠ hamad.alizai@lums.edu.pk

Dr. Luca Mottola

Professor,
Dipartimento di Elettronica,
Politecnico di Milano, Italy

⊠ luca.mottola@polimi.it

Dr. Kasim Sinan

Associate Professor,
Department of Computer Science
University of Trento, Italy

⋈ kasimsinan.yildirim@unitn.it

Dr. Junaid Haroon Siddiqui

Associate Professor,

Department of Computer Science

LUMS, Pakistan

⊠ junaid.siddiqui@lums.edu.pk

Dr. Bashima Islam

Assistant Professor,
School of Science and Engineering
Worcester Polytechnic Institute

⋈ bislam@wpi.edu

Dr. Josiah Hester

Associate Professor,
School of Interactive Computing
Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, USA

i josiah@gatech.edu

Last Updated: May 25, 2023